Jack Kapp Collection
Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress
- "Well I followed your advice. I turned the lights down low and played romantic music!" undated, Cartoon #42; Reckas, George; 1 drawing: pen and ink, blue wash (Box 5)
  A young woman complains to her mother while a sailor snores on the couch, oblivious to the records she's been playing.
- "Shyness compels Mr. Winterbottom to deliver his speech from a home recording," 1948 January 26, Cartoon #43; Reed, Ed; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  At a board meeting, the arms of a man hidden behind the table place a record on a turntable.
  "1948, the Register and Tribune Syndicate."
  Autographed by the artist: "All best wishes, To Jack Kapp -- Ed Reed -- "Off the Record."
- A cobra transfixed by music from a record player, undated, Cartoon #44; Richter, Mischa, 1910-; 1 drawing: pen and ink, white paint (Box 2)
  Autographed by the artist: "To Mr. Kapp -- Mischa Richter."
- "It's nice of you to contribute your phonograph records to the canteen, Ethel -- even if they are all nursery rhymes," 1943 February 6, Cartoon #45; Coe, Roland, 1906-1954; 1 drawing: pen and ink, charcoal (Box 2)
  The image shows girl scouts carrying records.
- "Open this package, Jack," circa 1947 January 29, Cartoon #46; Russell, Bruce, 1903-1963; 1 drawing: pen and ink on brown kraft paper (Box 8)
  On paper used to wrap a package that was mailed in 1947 (at top right are canceled stamps dated January 29, 1947), Russell has drawn a record labeled "Decca Records," that includes the address of the record company owned by Jack Kapp. The "song" on the record is entitled "Open this package, Jack," and the "songwriter" is "Kapp." Along the bottom of the "record label" are musical notes surrounded by the words "Office of the president." At upper right is the return address: "From Bruce Russell, Los Angeles Times."
- "Martial music," undated, Cartoon #47; Russell, Bruce, 1903-1963; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 8)
  The cartoon shows a broken record labeled "China peace."
  Autographed by the artist: "To Jack Kapp with best wishes. Bruce Russell."
- "Nothing like this in Nazi Germany," 1942 November 4, #48; Seibel, Fred O. (Fred Otto), 1886-1969; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 5)
  A speaking head identified as "U.S. voters" rests on the turntable of a phonograph labeled "ballot box." Emanating from the horn are the words "voice of the people."
  Autographed by the artist: "To Jack Kapp with my compliments. Fred O. Seibel."
  The drawing is also signed by the artist, lower right. Handwritten under the autograph is: "Richmond Times-Dispatch, November 4, 1942."
- David and Goliath, 1948 January 3, Cartoon #49; Seibel, Fred O. (Fred Otto), 1886-1969; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 5)
  Armed with a sword and shielded by a record, a huge robot is nevertheless hit in the head with a rock flung from a slingshot by James C. Petrillo. The robot is labeled "machine age," and the words "Ban on recording" appear at the top of the cartoon.
  Autographed by the artist: "To Jack Kapp with my best wishes. Fred O. Siebel."
  The drawing is also signed by the artist, lower right.
- "Acme Second Hand Phonograph Record Company, Good morning, good morning, good morning, good ...," undated, Cartoon #50; Soglow, Otto, 1900-1975; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  A switchboard operator speaks into a receiver.
  Autographed by the artist, lower left: "O. Soglow."
- "I can't figger it out at all -- no tubes or batteries!" undated, Cartoon #51; Spaar, William; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  Several natives comment on a playing phonograph while a pipe-smoking man in a safari outfit stands by.
- "Don't bother Junior now. He's listening to his homework," undated, Cartoon #52; Strauss, Charles; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  A boy listens to a record as his parents look on.
- "Swelling the chorus!" circa 1948, Cartoon #53; Talburt, Harold M., 1895-1966; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 5)
  "John L." (probably John L. Lewis, president of the United Mine Workers of America, 1920-1960) sings "Brother, can you spare a dime?" while a phonograph labeled "[James C.] Petrillo's royalty racket" plays. The musical notes floating from the phonograph have dollar signs on them, and Lewis holds a sign that states, "Demand of 10 cents a ton royalty for miner's union."
  Autographed by the artist: "To Jack Kapp with best wishes. H. M. Talburt."
  The drawing is also signed "Talburt" at lower left.
  In 1948, the year of the second American Federation of Musicians recording ban, the UMWA under president John L. Lewis won health and pension benefits for miners, financed partially by a royalty on every ton of coal mined.
- "The music goes round and round -- but it don't come out here!" between 1940 and 1950, Cartoon #54; Talburt, Harold M., 1895-1966; 1 print: lithograph, crayon (Box 6)
  While a record spins on the turntable, James C. Petrillo sits in the horn of a phonograph, blocking the sound.
  The Hodgson-Riley song, "The Music Goes Round and Round," recorded in 1935, was Decca Records' first hit, putting Jack Kapp's company in the black for the first time.
- "The super juke box," 1942, Cartoon #55; Thomas, Burt; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  Uncle Sam stands in front of a jukebox on which sits James C. Petrillo's head (bearing a definite resemblance to Italian dictator Benito Mussolini). A hand reaches out from the jukebox, which is labeled, "Pay me."
  Published in the Detroit News.
  Autographed by the artist: "To Jack Kapp with compliments of B. Thomas."
- A man looks through a pile of records as guests wait, undated, Cartoon #56; Tobin, Don; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  One of the guests says, "Really, Charley, I didn't mean for you to go to all that trouble. We can hear 'Sugar Blues' some other time."
- Jelly Bean Jones. "Gee I never really appreciated symphonies before -- they scale better than anything," 1948 March 10, Cartoon #57; Walter, Frank; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  Two children are throwing records.
- Jelly Bean Jones. "Look, Pop -- I've just invented a new game," 1948 January 14, Cartoon #58; Walter, Frank; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 2)
  A child jumps onto a record player as his father walks in.
- "The timid soul," 1946 September 2, Cartoon #59; Webster, Harold Tucker, 1885-1952; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 6)
  Standing near a record player and holding a record, Casper Milquetoast says, "Perhaps I'd better employ a couple of musicians to play this record for me. I don't want to offend the union and have them denounce me as a labor baiter, or a stooge for the capitalists, or a fascist."
  Signed by the artist, lower right.
- "The thrill that comes once in a lifetime," 1944 October 25, Cartoon #60; Webster, Harold Tucker, 1885-1952; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 6)
  A mother listens to the voice of her son on a record from the U.S.O.: "A -- hem -- uh -- ah -- er -- Well, -- ah -- gosh! I don't know what to say -- uh...." The mother, smiling, says, "Now, isn't that cute?"
- Two fairies near a bell-shaped flower, undated, Cartoon #61; Wheelan, Albertine Randall; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 6)
  A. R. Wheelan was a nineteenth-century cartoonist known for his Dumbunnies newspaper series.
  Handwritten caption under the first panel: "Adventuros [sic] fairy: 'Why this must be a phonograph! Doesn't that Bumble Bee's voice sound natural?'" Caption under the second panel: "Bee, appearing from within flower: 'Good morning ladies! This is my busy day. Aren't you out rather late?'"
  Signed by the artist, first panel, lower right.
- Woman reading album notes, 1942, Cartoon #62; Williams, Gluyas, 1888-1982; 1 drawing: pen and ink, blue pencil (Box 6)
  A woman looks puzzled as she reads the pretentious program notes accompanying the record she holds.
  Published in the New Yorker.
- A woman listens to her husband singing "Pistol Packin' Mama" in the shower, undated, Cartoon #63; Chenoweth, Hugh; 1 drawing: pen and ink
  Not on shelf.
- "Maestro Petrillo versus the law," undated, Cartoon #64; [Kay?]; 1 drawing: pen and ink, charcoal
  James C. Petrillo on a phonograph; a hand is jutting into the picture holding an injunction.
- The Goodrich Rubber Man's vacation, circa 1900, Cartoon #65; 1 print (poster) (Box 9)
  This promotional poster, printed for the Buffalo-Pan American Exposition of 1900 and 1901, was intended for distribution to Goodrich's wholesalers. The photographs of the salesmen-musicians superimposed over the drawing are of actual Goodrich Rubber Company employees.
- "Round 2," 1944 October, Cartoon #66; Berryman, James Thomas, 1902-1971; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 6)
  Uncle Sam, standing in the middle of a boxing ring, holds up a card that says “Round 2.” In one corner, Frank Sinatra sings into a microphone for sitting boxer FDR, and in the other, Bing Crosby croons into a microphone for Thomas Dewey.
  Published in the Washington Evening Star.
  Autographed by the artist: "Jim Berryman. With my best to my friend ... and everybody's friend, Bing!"
- "In full bloom," 1907 February 6, Cartoon #67; Glackens, L. M. (Louis M.), 1866-1933; 1 print: lithograph, color; 1 print: lithograph, black and white (Box 6)
  An inebriated man ("Mr. Talksome") stands in front of a window display of phonographs and declares, "Hones' fact, itsh the finesht display er mornin' glories ever shaw in m'life!"
  A black and white print matted on the reverse of the color print is the same image but includes the hand-written caption and editorial markings.
  Probably published in Puck magazine.
- "In the jungle," 1894, Cartoon #68; Glackens, L. M. (Louis M.), 1866-1933; 1 drawing: pen and ink (Box 6)
  A professor wearing a safari hat plays a phonograph from inside a zoo cage labeled "Prof. Monk, the scientist." Monkeys, some wearing human clothing, listen from outside the cage.
  Handwritten in pencil on reverse: "In the jungle. May 16, 1894."
  Stamp on reverse: "Keppler & Schwartzmann, 'Puck,' April 17, 1894, New York."
- Framed album cover of Oklahoma! 1946, 1 photomechanical print: in wooden frame (Box 11)
  Cover of the 1943 cast album, Selections from the Theatre Guild Musical Play Oklahoma!, featuring members of the original New York production. Decca album no. 359, 23M, Personality series.
  Inscription on the small metal plaque attached to the center of the album cover: "For Jack. This 500,001st album from Dick and [Deen?]. Feb. 3, 1946."
For more information about the collection, as well as Jack Kapp, James C. Petrillo, and the American recording industry in the first half of the 20th century, see Samuel Brylawski, "Cartoons for the Record: the Jack Kapp Collection," Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, volume 38, number 3 (summer 1981), pages 180-195.